Voice quality. You know how you hear a voice across a crowded room and you can
just tell that it's American? What's at play there? To answer that question, let's
first define our terms. What is voice quality in the American sound? It's a
combination of vocal placement and cadence. This means a throaty sound and a
stair-step intonation. Listen to British comedian Eddie Izzard imitate the American
accent. President Kennedy became the president of the United States of America.
And he went to Berlin. And he said, people of Berlin, people of Berlin. I can't do an
impression of President Kennedy, so they said, people of Berlin. Notice how his
voice moves back in his throat and down in his chest when he's imitating the American
accent. This throaty quality is an essential characteristic. There's even a
fancy word to describe it, rhoticity, which is that solid R as in hard and far. There
are regional dialects that are notable for lacking rhoticity, such as the classic
Bostonian, pack your car and have a yard for park your car in Harvard Yard, but the
overwhelming majority of Americans growl out the R. Intonation, voice quality, and
phrasing all contribute to the uniquely American voice, along with a casual
relaxed attitude. This relaxation causes American English to differ from the
crisper sounds of British English. Within voice quality, you'll be adjusting your
volume, a little louder versus muted or murmured, pitch, high-pitched versus a
deeper register, airflow, popped, hissed, or buzzed, and where the voice is
generated, throat and chest versus head and nose. Americans tend to be a little
louder than you're accustomed to. The stereotypical American is louder, a little
brasher, more boisterous, immediately friendly, informal, and slightly jokey.
It's important to project your voice out with more force than usual, and you'll
need more breath to push it out. Kids are loud, right? Things stick in their heads
because they yell them out. Yell this out! In the privacy of your home, car, or
mountaintop, get out and yell some of these sounds and practice sentences so
that you can get it really in your head. Don't be afraid to exaggerate and go way
further than you think the American accent actually is. This will help you embrace
the sound.